Continuing Studies fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Continuing Studies fonds
1965 - 2004
F-94
4.57 m of textual records 11 photographs 2 contact sheets 1 artifact
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
DATE RANGE Predominant dates of the records are 1970-1999. Only one file has a pre-1970 date (1965) and contains the "Report to the Presidents of the Three Public Universities in British Columbia." Thirteen files in Series 5 (Publications) contain post-1999 material comprised primarily of printed matter (course calendars, posters and brochures).
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Government of Canada through Library and Archives Canada and the Canadian Council of Archives' Control of Holdings Program (January 2005).
Continuing Studies
The Division of Continuing Education was formed in 1971 in order to develop new academic programs and to improve the accessibility of Simon Fraser University to the community. Milton McClaren, Director of the new division reported directly to the Vice-President, Academic. The original terms of reference for the Division of Continuing Education were very broad as the Senate had given it responsibility for courses of instruction offered at "times other than the usual times, in places other than the usual places, and in ways other than the normal ways." A few years later the Senate passed a series of motions which more precisely defined and described the role of the Division and established new procedures for offering and approving non-credit courses. By 1973 the Division of Continuing Education offered several types of programs including evening credit courses for undergraduates and graduates; summer session credit courses (primarily for teachers); off campus courses; and non-credit courses, lecture series and workshops.
In 1974 the Program for Senior Citizens was created with the assistance of a government grant. Using the "Age of Options" television program it was able to reach out to seniors in Burnaby and in the surrounding communities. Continuing Education further expanded its student base in 1974 by offering courses in interior and non-metropolitan locations such as the Fraser Valley and Kelowna. In 1975 Dr. Jack Blaney, previously the Associate Director of the Centre for Continuing Education at the University of British Columbia, replaced McClaren as the Dean of the newly renamed Division of Continuing Studies. With this appointment, Blaney became Canada's first Dean of Continuing Studies. The Center for Distance Education was established in the same year and introduced four university correspondence courses to fifty-five registered students. In 1976 the Division of Continuing Studies approved the Extended Studies Diploma that enabled students with an undergraduate degree to undertake further study outside of a traditional graduate program.
Backed by encouraging enrollment numbers, a proposal was circulated in late 1978 calling for a downtown program that would provide increased access to the university and support existing campus programs. In February 1980 SFU Downtown officially opened at a storefront location at 822 Howe Street and offered a selection of credit courses for degree completion, career upgrading, and personal interest and development. Organized under a Coordinator of Downtown Programs, courses were structured in six thematic areas: Business and Professional Studies; Urban and Regional Studies; Canadian Studies; Humanities; Health and Fitness Studies; and Social Sciences. The success of the programs soon led to the establishment of the Downtown Education Centre (DEC), a shared space with BCIT located at 549 Howe Street. In 1984 the Downtown Campus Planning Committee presented an interim report to the Senate Committee on Academic Priorities (SCAP) focusing on areas of program development. As a result, the School for Liberal and Professional Studies was established and used as a vehicle for organizing and marketing downtown-based, non-credit continuing studies courses on behalf of departments and faculties. By 1985 downtown programs included the Writing Program, the City Program, the Fine Arts Program and the Professional and Management Studies Program.
During this time Blaney was appointed as Vice-President, University Development and Extension while continuing to direct Continuing Studies. Blaney, considered the architect of Continuing Studies at SFU, spearheaded the concept of the university's new campus at Harbour Centre. Opened in 1989 in the historic Spencer Building at 515 West Hastings, the downtown campus was built entirely thorough private sector funding due in part to the strong fundraising efforts of the "Bridge to the Future Campaign." After almost ten years of planning and development, SFU's new downtown campus opened with a curriculum of unique, established programs and specialized spaces that included an arts studio, human performance centre, conference centre, and language and computer laboratories.
In the mid-1980's, Continuing Studies initiated two very distinct, off-campus programs. In 1984 the Prison Education Program (PEP) was launched under contract with the Federal Government. For ten years, Continuing Studies administered the program at four penitentiaries - Kent, Matsqui, Mountain, and William Head/Metchosin - and offered inmates courses in the Liberal Arts leading to certificate, degree and diploma completion in several academic disciplines. In 1988, the division created an academic partnership with the Secwepemc Cultural Education Society (SCES) to develop a university program for native students. The Kamloops-based integrated university program was structured with an emphasis on Native studies and social sciences and students were able to earn a BA degree with a major in Sociology or Anthropology.
Meanwhile at the Burnaby campus, Continuing Studies programs and courses continued to grow. After serving as Assistant Dean for three years, Jo Lynne Hoegg was appointed Dean of Continuing Studies in 1984 (a position she would hold until 1994.) The Applied Sciences Continuing Education Program began offering specialized non-credit courses for local and international audiences, including computer programming courses, a project management program, and in 1986, the Management Skills in Advanced Technology (MSAT) program. Utilizing a medium found in most households, Continuing Studies worked with KCTS/9 and the Knowledge Network to air television programs developed for distance education courses. Through funding from the BC Ministry of Skills, Labour and Training, the Centre for Distance Education Lab was established in 1995. It was later expanded and renamed the LohnLab in 1997 because of a financial donation from the Earl and Jennie Lohn Foundation. From 1998-1999 Lynn Elen Burton served as Dean and was succeeded by Colin Yerbury in 1999, the current Dean of Continuing Studies.
In 2000, the Morris J. Wosk Centre for Dialogue, a state of the art conference centre devoted to facilitating public and private dialogue, opened across the street from Harbour Centre. Continuing Studies is responsible for the program component of the Centre, which, since its opening, has won worldwide acclaim for its design. SFU's newest campus location in Surrey (opened in 2002), also offers continuing studies courses and professional development programs for students.
In 2004 the Seniors' Program celebrated its 29th anniversary. It remains an integral part of SFU's commitment to "help adults achieve their intellectual, professional and cultural goals through programs for lifelong learning that build on the strengths of the university and resources of the community." The program continues to offer intellectually challenging non-credit courses each week and it is open to anyone fifty-five years of age and older regardless of their educational background. Tuition is free for seniors sixty years of age or older and a Senior Citizens Certificate is available for those who complete thirty hours of courses.
Continuing Studies continues to expand its curriculum every year, developing courses, seminars and workshops in each of its current programming units. As of 2005, they included the Centre for Distance Education, the Centre for Integrated and Credit Studies and the Center for Community and Professional Programs.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
The fonds consists of records relating to the development and administration of the Continuing Studies program and its predecessors. Activities, topics and events documented include the Dean's correspondence with university departments, faculties, and external organizations; participation on university and inter-university committees on continuing education; development of credit and non-credit courses, programs, seminars, workshops, and conferences; and publications.
The types of documents include meeting agendas, minutes, and supporting papers; correspondence and reports; annual reports; budgets and financial working papers; contracts; teaching and program evaluations; course outlines, proposals, and planning materials; and publications including course calendars, oversized posters, brochures, and journals. Also included are photographs, contact sheets and one artifact.
The arrangement of the fonds into series, sub-series, and sub-sub-series was provided by the archivist after consultation with Continuing Studies staff in November 2004. Within each series, sub-series, and sub-sub-series, files are arranged chronologically. Over the course of time, various credit and non-credit programs moved among different organizational units of Continuing Studies. Therefore, Series 3 (Credit Programs) and Series 4 (Non-credit Programs) were established to reflect the content of the courses rather than the course's location in a particular unit.
Burton, Lynn Elen; Blaney, Jack P.; Hoegg, Jo Lynne; McClaren, Milton; Yerbury, J. Colin; Photographic materials; Artefacts; Textual records
The records were received by the Simon Fraser University Archives through the regular application of university Records Retention Schedules and Disposal Authorities (RRSDAs).
Additional material has been accessioned but not yet processed (as of December 2004: 67 cm., 1992-1996). Please consult the archivist for information about using these materials; restrictions may apply. Further accruals are expected.
Records relating to Continuing Studies and the planning and delivery of multi-disciplinary programs can also be found in a number of departmental and faculty fonds including the Faculty of Arts (F-2), the Department of Archaelogy (F-4), Department of Biological Sciences (F-5), Department of Languages, Literature and Linguistics (F-13), Department of Physics (F-19), Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies (F-23), Department of History (F-26), Office of Analytical Studies (F-52), School of Kinesiology (F-60), Centre for Canadian Studies (F-64), School of Communication (F-92), School for the Contemporary Arts (F-109), and TeleLearning Network Inc. (F-172). Further correspondence, program development and reports can also be found in the Office of the Vice-President, Finance and Administration (F-28), Office of the Vice-President, Academic (F-29), Senate (F-84), Office of the President (F-193), and Office of the Vice President for Harbour Centre and Continuing Studies (F-108, not yet processed).
The fonds includes records containing personal information. As such, access to some files may be restricted in accordance with the provisions of British Columbia's Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy Act (RSBC 1996 c. 165). Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File and item lists are available.
- Dean's correspondence, 1970 - 1998; F-94-1; 27 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the Dean's correspondence with campus and non-campus organizations. Activities, events and topics documented include dean's/director's meetings and reports; liaison with university departments and faculties regarding continuing education; television networks including KCTS/9, the Knowledge Network and CanWest Pacific Television; and development and administration of the Downtown Education Centre and SFU at Harbour Centre. Records include agendas and minutes, correspondence, annual reports, working papers and reports.
  - Correspondence, 1970 - 1974; F-94-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - Dean / Director reports, 1971 - 1973; F-94-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - Annual reports, 1971 - 1973; F-94-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - Articulation of university resources, 1972; F-94-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - SFU - Arts, Economics, 1974 - 1979; F-94-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - SFU - Arts, Languages, Literatures and Linguistics, 1974 - 1980; F-94-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - Space, 1974 - 1982; F-94-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - SFU - Arts, Psychology, 1974 - 1984; F-94-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - SFU - Arts, Sociology, Anthropology, 1975 - 1983; F-94-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - SFU - Arts, Philosophy, 1975 - 1983; F-94-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - SFU - Arts, Division of General Studies, 1975 - 1984; F-94-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - Status and Directions of Continuing Studies at SFU, 1976; F-94-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 94-8)
  - SFU - School of Criminology, 1978 - 1983; F-94-1-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
  - Planning, 1980 - 1981; F-94-1-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
    Open
  - Downtown Education Centre/SFU Downtown, 1980 - 1981; F-94-1-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
  - KCTS/9, vol. 1, 1980 - 1987; F-94-1-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
  - KCTS/9, vol. 2, 1980 - 1987; F-94-1-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
  - Knowledge Network of the West, vol. 1, 1981 - 1982; F-94-1-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
  - Knowledge Network of the West, vol. 2, 1981 - 1982; F-94-1-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
  - Dean's meetings, 1984 - 1985; F-94-1-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
  - Canadian Association for University Continuing Education (CAUCE), 1984 - 1991; F-94-1-0-0-21 (Archival box - standard 94-9)
  - CanWest Pacific Television Inc. (CPTV), 1986; F-94-1-0-0-22 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
  - SFU at Harbour Centre, 1988 - 1998; F-94-1-0-0-23 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
    - SFU Harbour Centre engraved paperweight, [199-?]; F-94-1-0-0-23-1 (Three-dimensional object: steel OBJ-3977)
      Artefacts
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-94-item2.
- Committees, 1965 - 1988; F-94-2; 35 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the Dean's involvement on or liaison with various university and inter-university committees related to continuing studies/education. Records include agendas, minutes, correspondence, reports and working papers.
  - Asia Pacific Advisory Committee, 1984 - 1988; F-94-2-1; 1 cm of textual records
    Asia Pacific Advisory Committee
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1984 - 1988; F-94-2-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
  - Inter-University Committee on Continuing Education, 1971 - 1978; F-94-2-2; 5 cm of textual records
    Inter-University Committee on Continuing Education
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1971; F-94-2-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1972; F-94-2-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1973; F-94-2-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
    - Correspondence and working papers, 1974; F-94-2-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1977 - 1978; F-94-2-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
  - Joint University Ad Hoc Committee on Continuing Education, 1965; F-94-2-3; 1 cm of textual records
    Joint University Ad Hoc Committee on Continuing Education
    - Report to the Presidents of the Three Public Universities in British Columbia, 1965; F-94-2-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
  - Senate Committee on Continuing Studies, 1974 - 1984; F-94-2-4; 16 cm of textual records
    Senate Committee on Continuing Studies
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 1, 1974 - 1979; F-94-2-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 2, 1974 - 1979; F-94-2-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 3, 1974 - 1979; F-94-2-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 94-10)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 1, 1980 - 1981; F-94-2-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 94-11)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 2, 1980 - 1981; F-94-2-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 94-11)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 1, 1982; F-94-2-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 94-11)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 2, 1982; F-94-2-4-0-7 (Archival box - standard 94-11)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1982 - 1983; F-94-2-4-0-8 (Archival box - standard 94-11)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1984; F-94-2-4-0-9 (Archival box - standard 94-11)
  - Tri-University Committee on Distance Education, 1975 - 1980; F-94-2-5; 8 cm of textual records
    Tri-University Committee on Distance Education
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 1, 1975 - 1980; F-94-2-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 94-12)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 2, 1975 - 1980; F-94-2-5-0-2 (Archival box - standard 94-12)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1978; F-94-2-5-0-3 (Archival box - standard 94-12)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 1, 1978 - 1979; F-94-2-5-0-4 (Archival box - standard 94-12)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 2, 1978 - 1979; F-94-2-5-0-5 (Archival box - standard 94-12)
  - Universitities Council of British Columbia (UCBC), 1974 - 1984; F-94-2-6; 3 cm of textual records
    Universities Council of British Columbia
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 1, 1974 - 1984; F-94-2-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 94-12)
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, vol. 2, 1974 - 1984; F-94-2-6-0-2 (Archival box - standard 94-12)
  - University Review Committee, 1977 - 1978; F-94-2-7; 2 cm of textual records
    University Review Committee
    - Correspondence, minutes and working papers, 1977 - 1978; F-94-2-7-0-1 (Archival box - standard 94-12)
- Credit Programs, 1974 - 1998; F-94-3; 2.37 m of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the administration and development of university credit courses and programs offered by Continuing Studies. Records consist of correspondence and working papers, reports, student handbooks, course guides and oversized posters, budget and financial working papers, meeting minutes, statistics, course proposals, outlines and evaluations, contracts, and publications.
  - Distance Education Program, 1974 - 1992; F-94-3-1; 56 cm of textual records
    The Distance Education Program at SFU began in 1975 and has since grown to be one of the largest distance education programs in Canada. Working in partnership with academic departments, the Centre for Distance Education administers the program. Through directed independent study (correspondence) or online study students can complete courses leading to majors, minors, certificates, diplomas, and in the case of the Bachelor of General Studies, a full degree. As of 2005, more than one hundred university credit courses are offered per year.
    Sub-series consists of records relating to the administration and delivery of the Distance Education Program. Activities, events and topics documented include the operation of the Centre for Distance Education, liaison with departments regarding the Directed Independent Study program and correspondence courses, Knowledge Network telecourses, and administration of the South Pacific Nutrition Project. Records include correspondence, minutes, policies and procedures, student handbooks, budget and financial working papers, reports, and Knowledge Network telecourse guides and curriculum posters.
    - Centre for Distance Education, 1975 - 1992; F-94-3-1-1; 26 cm of textual records
      Centre for Online and Distance Education
      - Distance Education - non-credit programs, 1975 - 1991; F-94-3-1-1-1 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Library correspondence, 1975 - 1992; F-94-3-1-1-2 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Distance Education - KCTS, 1980 - 1989; F-94-3-1-1-3 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Mail strike procedures, 1981 - 1985; F-94-3-1-1-4 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Bookstore correspondence, 1981 - 1991; F-94-3-1-1-5 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Staffing matters, 1981 - 1991; F-94-3-1-1-6 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Teleconferencing, 1982 - 1992; F-94-3-1-1-7 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Telecourses, 1983 - 1990; F-94-3-1-1-8 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - SFU Publications, 1984 - 1986; F-94-3-1-1-9 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - British Columbia Educational Credit Bank, 1984 - 1990; F-94-3-1-1-10 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Resource and Development Program planning, 1985 - 1987; F-94-3-1-1-11 (Archival box - standard 94-13)
      - Voluntary and Non-profit Sector Management Program correspondence, 1985 - 1989; F-94-3-1-1-12 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Certificate in Liberal Arts - correspondence and working papers, 1985 - 1990; F-94-3-1-1-13 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Distance Education Opportunity Committee, 1986 - 1987; F-94-3-1-1-14 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Promotions Committee, 1986 - 1990; F-94-3-1-1-15 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Commonwealth of Learning, vol. 1, 1986 - 1991; F-94-3-1-1-16 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Commonwealth of Learning, vol. 2, 1986 - 1991; F-94-3-1-1-17 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Continuing Education Deans and Directors Committee, 1987 - 1991; F-94-3-1-1-18 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Knowledge Network correspondence, 1989 - 1991; F-94-3-1-1-19 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Centre for Distance Education - tutor and student handbooks, [199-?]; F-94-3-1-1-20 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - Distance Education correspondence, 1990 - 1992; F-94-3-1-1-21 (Archival box - standard 94-14)
      - SFU Educational Telecommunications Project Committee, 1991 - 1992; F-94-3-1-1-22 (Archival box - standard 94-15)
      - Centre for Distance Education - Three Year Planning Report, 1992; F-94-3-1-1-23 (Archival box - standard 94-15)
    - Directed Independent Study Courses (DISC / DIS), 1974 - 1985; F-94-3-1-2; 6 cm of textual records
      - DISC correspondence - English, 1974 - 1980; F-94-3-1-2-1 (Archival box - standard 94-15)
      - DISC correspondence - Faculty of Arts, 1975 - 1980; F-94-3-1-2-2 (Archival box - standard 94-15)
      - DISC correspondence - History, 1975 - 1981; F-94-3-1-2-3 (Archival box - standard 94-15)
      - DISC correspondence - Geography, 1975 - 1981; F-94-3-1-2-4 (Archival box - standard 94-15)
      - DISC correspondence - Political Science, 1976 - 1979; F-94-3-1-2-5 (Archival box - standard 94-15)